Guide to the NYU Abu Dhabi Capstone Archives AD.MC.004
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
- Engineering Division Projects, 2014-2021
  - Mechanical Engineering
    - Abdouli, Nayef, and Coezette Sibanda. High-throughput Micro-Fluidic Chip for Optogenetic Studies of Neuromuscular Diseases Using C. Elegans., 2016; 2016-0021; 7988; Human neuromuscular diseases are as common as 1 in 3000 people. Examples of these diseases include Duchenne and Becker muscular d
      Human neuromuscular diseases are as common as 1 in 3000 people. Examples of these diseases include Duchenne and Becker muscular dystrophies, amyotrophic lateral sclerosis, and these affect people and societies both physically and emotionally. Neuromuscular diseases lead to progressive loss in motor function and premature mortality. Vertebrate animal models have been for a long time used to study these diseases. These models however are expensive and slow. Newer models of using C elegans worms for studying neuromuscular diseases are under pursuit and growing rapidly. These models present the possibility to carry out the studies in a cost-efficient and high-throughput manner. There are challenges associated with the use of C-elegans worms however, due to the small sizes of the worms. These challenges include mainly automated handling and precise neural stimulation.
    - Mahomed, Abdullah Ismail, Nkos'khona Msimanga, and Eder Munyampenda. Water Filtration Using Plant Xylem., 2016; 2016-0019; 7990; Our capstone project aims to address the global void in cost effective water filtration. Every year, millions of people die from waterborne diseases caused by bacteria and viruses due to lack of access to clean water. This tragic fact creates a need for solutions specifically targeted towards the lower-income demographic in the developing world. Based on a research paper published in 2014, gymnosperm plant xylem was identified as a suitable filtering material. Plant xylem's inner structure is uniquely suited for water filtration due to nanoscale pores located between its water carrying channels called tracheids. These nano-pores are the vehicle of filtration capable of removing 99% of bacteria and particles larger than 100 nm. The goal of the project was to design a product that would provide individuals in developing countries with a method of taking advantage of xylem's filtering properties in an easy and cost-effective manner. The project design ultimately resulted in a two-piece plastic filter containment unit, whose cap is permanently attached to a jerry can, and whose xylem holder screws into the cap and contains eight holes to place xylem through. This paper describes the design process and an analysis of the final product. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2016-0019)
      Our capstone project aims to address the global void in cost effective water filtration. Every year, millions of people die from waterborne diseases caused by bacteria and viruses due to lack of access to clean water. This tragic fact creates a need for solutions specifically targeted towards the lower-income demographic in the developing world. Based on a research paper published in 2014, gymnosperm plant xylem was identified as a suitable filtering material. Plant xylem's inner structure is uniquely suited for water filtration due to nanoscale pores located between its water carrying channels called tracheids. These nano-pores are the vehicle of filtration capable of removing 99% of bacteria and particles larger than 100 nm. The goal of the project was to design a product that would provide individuals in developing countries with a method of taking advantage of xylem's filtering properties in an easy and cost-effective manner. The project design ultimately resulted in a two-piece plastic filter containment unit, whose cap is permanently attached to a jerry can, and whose xylem holder screws into the cap and contains eight holes to place xylem through. This paper describes the design process and an analysis of the final product.
    - Abdallah, Said, Jean Edwards, and Tshering Gyaltshen. Concentrated Solar Powered Stirling Engine for Reverse Osmosis Desalination and Pumped Storage Hydroelectricity., 2017; 2017-0017; Said Abdallah, Tshering Gyaltshen: In recent years, there has been a rise in the demand of renewable energy because of the negative environmental impacts and their exhaustible nature. This has led to an increase in research in this field, to come up with new, innovative ways of satisfying this need. The most common form of renewable energy is solar energy, which is commonly utilized by converting the sun's rays of light into either electric or thermal energy. Although, countries like the United Arab Emirates have an abundance of non-renewable sources of energy such as oil, a lot of investment is being put into increasing the use of renewable energy sources in these regions. In the UAE, the government has set a goal to produce 25% of its energy renewably by 2030, a significant increase from the current levels of less than 1%. The aim of this project is to work towards the attaining of this goal and beyond, with a sustainable and cost-effective solution that makes use of the natural resources of the UAE. The proposed solution harvests solar energy with the help of Fresnel lens powered Stirling engines for both water desalination via reverse osmosis, and energy storage via a pumped storage hydroelectric system.; Jean Edwards: As of 2009, the UAE had a total primary energy supply of 2,526.8 PJ, of which ~1.0 PJ was from renewable sources (about 0.04%). The UAE has set goals to increase the proportion of renewable energy from the current levels of less than 1% to 25% by 2030. The aim of this project is to work towards the attaining of this goal and beyond, with a sustainable and cost-effective solution that makes use of the natural resources of the UAE. The proposed solution harvests solar energy with the help of Fresnel lens powered Stirling engines for both water desalination via reverse osmosis, and energy storage via a pumped storage hydroelectric system. Water desalination was addressed because it currently accounts for about 10% of the UAE's total energy consumption. The pumped storage system makes use of seawater as the working fluid, with reservoirs constructed on the UAE's natural Eastern mountain ranges located close to the sea, thereby addressing power generation requirements, grid energy storage needs and peak-load demands. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2017-0017)
      Said Abdallah, Tshering Gyaltshen: In recent years, there has been a rise in the demand of renewable energy because of the negative environmental impacts and their exhaustible nature. This has led to an increase in research in this field, to come up with new, innovative ways of satisfying this need. The most common form of renewable energy is solar energy, which is commonly utilized by converting the sun's rays of light into either electric or thermal energy. Although, countries like the United Arab Emirates have an abundance of non-renewable sources of energy such as oil, a lot of investment is being put into increasing the use of renewable energy sources in these regions. In the UAE, the government has set a goal to produce 25% of its energy renewably by 2030, a significant increase from the current levels of less than 1%. The aim of this project is to work towards the attaining of this goal and beyond, with a sustainable and cost-effective solution that makes use of the natural resources of the UAE. The proposed solution harvests solar energy with the help of Fresnel lens powered Stirling engines for both water desalination via reverse osmosis, and energy storage via a pumped storage hydroelectric system.
      Jean Edwards: As of 2009, the UAE had a total primary energy supply of 2,526.8 PJ, of which ~1.0 PJ was from renewable sources (about 0.04%). The UAE has set goals to increase the proportion of renewable energy from the current levels of less than 1% to 25% by 2030. The aim of this project is to work towards the attaining of this goal and beyond, with a sustainable and cost-effective solution that makes use of the natural resources of the UAE. The proposed solution harvests solar energy with the help of Fresnel lens powered Stirling engines for both water desalination via reverse osmosis, and energy storage via a pumped storage hydroelectric system. Water desalination was addressed because it currently accounts for about 10% of the UAE's total energy consumption. The pumped storage system makes use of seawater as the working fluid, with reservoirs constructed on the UAE's natural Eastern mountain ranges located close to the sea, thereby addressing power generation requirements, grid energy storage needs and peak-load demands.
    - de la Chapelle, Witold, Ting-Che Lin, and Xiao Lu. Product Design for Manufacture, Reliability and Marketing of a Device to Predict Plant Strength., 2017; 2017-0021; Yield losses in maize (Zea mays L.) due to stalk lodging has significant negative economic impact. The lodging resistance in maize could be advanced more rapidly with the development of selective breeding tools that accurately predict stalk strength. Motivated by the strong correlation between flexural stiffness and stalk strength, a device that measures flexural rigidity was developed to predict stalk strength. To allow for a wider adaptation of such device, this Capstone aims to produce a second iteration of such device that is more accessible and robust. This is achieved through the integration of an intuitive graphical user interface, the redesign of mechanical structure to improve ergonomic comfort and robustness, and the refinement of electronics for more accurate data collection. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2017-0021)
      Yield losses in maize (Zea mays L.) due to stalk lodging has significant negative economic impact. The lodging resistance in maize could be advanced more rapidly with the development of selective breeding tools that accurately predict stalk strength. Motivated by the strong correlation between flexural stiffness and stalk strength, a device that measures flexural rigidity was developed to predict stalk strength. To allow for a wider adaptation of such device, this Capstone aims to produce a second iteration of such device that is more accessible and robust. This is achieved through the integration of an intuitive graphical user interface, the redesign of mechanical structure to improve ergonomic comfort and robustness, and the refinement of electronics for more accurate data collection.
    - Aboulhassan, Rami Haytham, Simeret Genet, Sahan Tampoe, and William Young. Solar-Driven Absorption Air Conditioner, 2018; 2018-0046; The purpose of this capstone project was to design, build and test a single-effect absorption refrigeration cycle that uses solar energy as the sole source of energy. Design goals were focused on low toxicity, sustainability, reliability and therefore, applicability to urban environments. Conventional vapor compression cycles use electricity and emit gases that cause air pollution and therefore, there is a strong imperative to create an alternative. The main drawbacks of the current absorption refrigeration systems, which use ammonia or lithium bromide working fluids, are: 1. Ammonia is highly toxic, flammable and explosive. 2. Lithium bromide is expensive and has the issue of crystallization at a range of temperatures, pressures and concentrations. Thus, in this capstone project, ethylene glycol was used as an absorption medium for the working fluid (water). Specifically, the design process included: 1. Optimization of the size of the absorber to get a coefficient of performance (COP) higher than 0.67. 2. Decreasing the heat loss from the desorber to increase the COP. 3. Preventing leakages when the cycle runs in a vacuum (pressure range from 1.5 kPa to 30 kPa) by using better-designed instruments. 4. Comprehensive data acquisition methods to get data from each component in the cycle. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0046)
      The purpose of this capstone project was to design, build and test a single-effect absorption refrigeration cycle that uses solar energy as the sole source of energy. Design goals were focused on low toxicity, sustainability, reliability and therefore, applicability to urban environments. Conventional vapor compression cycles use electricity and emit gases that cause air pollution and therefore, there is a strong imperative to create an alternative. The main drawbacks of the current absorption refrigeration systems, which use ammonia or lithium bromide working fluids, are: 1. Ammonia is highly toxic, flammable and explosive. 2. Lithium bromide is expensive and has the issue of crystallization at a range of temperatures, pressures and concentrations. Thus, in this capstone project, ethylene glycol was used as an absorption medium for the working fluid (water). Specifically, the design process included: 1. Optimization of the size of the absorber to get a coefficient of performance (COP) higher than 0.67. 2. Decreasing the heat loss from the desorber to increase the COP. 3. Preventing leakages when the cycle runs in a vacuum (pressure range from 1.5 kPa to 30 kPa) by using better-designed instruments. 4. Comprehensive data acquisition methods to get data from each component in the cycle.
    - Alvi, Zoha, and Keerthana Prakash. Water Filtration system for developing region, 2018; 2018-0048; Potable or drinkable water is defined as having acceptable quality in terms of its physical, chemical and bacteriological parameters so that it can be safely used for human consumption. Among the various water pollutants, biological contaminants are the most fatal in developing regions. The only possible way to achieve potable water is to carry out disinfection processes. According to the research conducted at MIT, nano-pores in Gymnosperm plant xylem has been identified as an efficient filter of bacteria due to the "short tracheid that would force water to flow through pit membranes". The availability of this plant in the region makes it an affordable and reliable source to be incorporated in a water filter device. In addition, adding a compartment for sand and charcoal each makes the water filter more efficient at filtering out the physical, chemical and biological contaminants. In this capstone project, we aim to achieve an advanced multi-step xylem-based filter that can filter bacteria and heavy metals without blockage problems at an economical cost to people residing in developing regions who do not have access to potable water. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0048)
      Potable or drinkable water is defined as having acceptable quality in terms of its physical, chemical and bacteriological parameters so that it can be safely used for human consumption. Among the various water pollutants, biological contaminants are the most fatal in developing regions. The only possible way to achieve potable water is to carry out disinfection processes. According to the research conducted at MIT, nano-pores in Gymnosperm plant xylem has been identified as an efficient filter of bacteria due to the "short tracheid that would force water to flow through pit membranes". The availability of this plant in the region makes it an affordable and reliable source to be incorporated in a water filter device. In addition, adding a compartment for sand and charcoal each makes the water filter more efficient at filtering out the physical, chemical and biological contaminants. In this capstone project, we aim to achieve an advanced multi-step xylem-based filter that can filter bacteria and heavy metals without blockage problems at an economical cost to people residing in developing regions who do not have access to potable water.
    - Aldhaheri, Sara, and Alexander Leigh MacKay. GLiDAR: Design Optimization and Active Stabilization of LiDAR Sensor Payload for Surveying, 2019; 2019-0060 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2019-0060)
      The GLiDAR Capstone endeavours to enable the production of three-dimensional models that support the monitoring of changes to geographical features over time.GLiDAR applies advancements in solid-state LiDAR (Light Imaging, Detection, and Ranging) technology to address the challenges of expense, iterability, and data collection scale experienced in other surveying methods.Developed as an attachment for the Lockheed Martin INDAGO 3 Unmanned Aerial System, GLiDAR contributes to the field of aerial surveying by enabling the generation of high-quality, localized data to support landmass tracking.
    - Almasi, Bence A., Amal Badri, Veronica Lee, and Ushna Usman. Building a Low Cost Turbidostat, 2019; 2019-0049 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2019-0049)
      Continuous culture devices can be used for various purposes such as establishing reproducible growth conditions or maintaining cell populations under a constant environment for long time periods. To more accurately characterize biological systems, researchers must turn to static environments, which yield lower noise in quantitative phenotyping. A primary tool for culturing cells in a static environment is continuous culture, where inoculated growth medium is continually diluted with fresh medium. Turbidostats are powerful characterization tools that provide static culture environments; however, they are often expensive, especially when purchased in custom configurations, and are difficult to design and construct in a lab. Eight culture chambers are controlled simultaneously with the proposed configuration, and all components are readily available from various sources. We demonstrate that our continuous culture device can be used under different modes, and can easily be programmed to behave either as a turbidostat or fluorostat. Addition of fresh medium to the culture vessel is to be controlled by a real-time feedback loop or simply calibrated to deliver a defined volume. The project aims to build a device which is both cheaper and less laborious in comparison to the already existing commercial versions.
    - Castillo, Alberto, Pratik Maisuria, and Mahmoud Soliman. Reconstructing the Horologium of Harun Al-Rashid, 2019; 2019-0066 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2019-0066)
      The following report details the reconstruction of the horologium of Harun al-Rashid from an engineering perspective. The purpose of the project is to rebuild the water clock in the closest resemblance possible to the original based on existing literature. Furthermore, the project aims to capture the essence of the clock as a landmark in human achievement. For this purpose the clock is to be reproduced with the same aesthetic artistry as the original, as well as the entirety of the operational mechanism. In the interest of practicality, the clock will first be built at scale, maintaining only the water regulation mechanisms at full size. A marvel of the ancient world, the engineered replica will stand a testament to the achievement and technicality of muslim engineers of the ancient world, namely Al-Jazari. In the long term, this capstone serves to mark the start of a project into tourism with a focus on the forgotten engineering marvels of the ancient muslim world.
    - Iqbal, Mubasher, and Saad Sultan. Paper Based Filter For Water Purification, 2019; 2019-0064 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2019-0064)
      Problems such as the inaccessibility of clean drinking water and the non-recycling of paper are very common in today's world. Even though steps have been taken to rectify these problems, most of the solutions that exist are either expensive, technical or inaccessible in a lot of regions around the world. This project hopes to solve the problem of the inaccessibility of clean drinking water by designing a device that uses a stack of compressed paper while also making an effort to resolve problems related to paper recycling. The aim is to make the device cheap, easy to handle and readily available. So far, we have conducted several tests and carried out trouble-shooting mechanism to solve leakage issues. Data is being collected to test the filtration-efficiency and steps are being taken to improve the flow-rate of the device.
    - Jeksen, Janar. Design of a continuous monitoring system for the Mineral Nutrient Uptake by Plants in Hydroponic System, 2019; 2019-0054 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2019-0054)
      Vertical farming is an agricultural method of growing plants where roots are ex- posed to the water solvent rich in mineral nutrients. It aids in food security by pro- viding control over all environmental factors, the preservation of endangered species of plants and the conservation of resources such as arable land and water. It is based on the finding that plants are best able to absorb particulate nutrients in a distance range of 1 to 50 micrometers (μm). Therefore, roots of the plants that are suspended within enclosed nutrient rich systems can better absorb and assimilate the minerals for more efficient farming with minimal water usage. Out of all available mineral nutrients, potassium ion (K+) plays particularly crucial role in plant growth and metabolism, and it is also the most abundant cation in plants. The project aims to develop a micro scale sensor that monitors the real time uptake of K+ via roots that are directly exposed to the nutrient solution. The data collected can be further used to optimize the amount of nutrients needed by plant thus minimizing nutrient waste and producing crops of higher nutritional value.
    - Kasahara, Shunsuke. Design of a Bio-inspired Lizard Robot Mimicking Tail Autotomy Process, 2019; 2019-0053 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2019-0053)
      Caudal autotomy is widespread among lizards: around 13 out of 20 families show this reflex severance strategy of their tails as a self-defence mechanism either to escape the predator's grasp or in anticipation of any life-threatening situation. The detached tail continues to wiggle (may go up to 30 minutes) through anaerobic metabolism and attracts the attention of the predator, which ultimately gives time to the lizard escape the ambush site. The mechanism of autotomy still remains secret. To explain this sheer bizarre phenomenon, we have developed a mechanistic model. Bio-inspired by the microstructures found on the broken tail surfaces, a bio-interlocking model containing an array of hemispherical microstructures was proposed. To test the model, a lab test setup was built and experiments on the biomimetic tail part were performed for its characterization. Finally, to demonstrate the actuatable interlock mechanism, a lizard robot was designed and fabricated. This robot detects incoming danger (incoming objects) and releases its tail while running away, as a real lizard would do. The robot and its tail shedding mechanism using the actuated bio-interlock was successfully tested.
    - Kedia, Raghav, Gjorgji Shemov, and Jotham Varghese. A Radio-controlled Car with Dual Power Sources of Solar and Battery, 2019; 2019-0047 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2019-0047)